<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology for the new separation in a letter to Dr. John Sharpe, Archbishop of York, occasioned by his farewell-sermon, preached on the 28th of June, at St. Giles's in the Fields.</title>
            <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12652</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13016925</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13016925</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96576</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43648)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96576)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 741:42)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology for the new separation in a letter to Dr. John Sharpe, Archbishop of York, occasioned by his farewell-sermon, preached on the 28th of June, at St. Giles's in the Fields.</title>
                  <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sharp, John, 1645-1714. --  Sermon preach'd June 28, 1691 at St. Giles in the Fields.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96576:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGY FOR THE New Separation: In a LETTER to Dr. <hi>John Sharpe,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>YORK;</hi> OCCASIONED By his Farewell-Sermon, preached on the 28th of <hi>June,</hi> at St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s in the Fields.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MALACHI 11.7, 8, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Prieſt's Lips <hi>ſhould</hi> keep Knowledge, and they <hi>ſhould</hi> ſeek the Law at his Mouth; for he is the Meſſenger of the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
               <p>But ye have departed out of the Way, ye have cauſed many to ſtumble at the Law, ye have corrupted the Covenant of <hi>Levi,</hi> ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
               <p>Therefore have I alſo made you contemptible and baſe before all the People, according at ye have not kept my ways, but have been partial in the Law.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96576:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96576:2"/>
            <head>To the Gentlemen of the Veſtry of St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s in the Fields.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Here preſent you with ſome Reflections upon the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York</hi>'s Farewel-Sermon, which <hi>his Grace</hi> tells us he Publiſhed at your Requeſt: They are written in form of Letter to him; and as I preſent them to you with as much Reſpect, and in as much Chriſtian Charity, as he, I believe, preſented the Sermon; ſo I hope you will read them with as much Candour, and examine impartially, without any byaſs to Perſons or Cauſes, which is in the Right, and whether the Things which you took upon his Grace's Authority, be ſo or no. I muſt do him the Juſtice to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, That he is an eminent Perſon in his Profeſſion, as well as in that ſtation which he now holds in the Church, and that he deſerves that Eſteem and Veneration which you have for him: But then I muſt tell you, That the Authority of no ſingle Man, or number of Men, how eminent or great ſoever, ought to ſignifie any thing with <hi>Church of England Men,</hi> againſt the Authority of the Church. I have ſeen her Articles and Homilies in many of the <hi>London-Veſtries;</hi> and if they be in yours, I deſire you to make them the Teſt of my Lord's Sermon, and this Anſwer to it, which I deſire may be approved, or rejected by you, as it happens to prove by that Teſt.</p>
            <p>See, I pray you, Gentlemen, if you can find any thing in them to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance transferring Allegiance from a living and claiming Legal King, or daily Praying for his deſtruction: See if you can find any thing in them that will juſtifie his Graces Expoſition of <hi>1 Tim. 11.1, 2.</hi> or of Submitting, or Praying for the Powers in being, without diſtinction or regard to Titles, which he ſays, <hi>Is the very Doctrine of the Church of England.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> If it be, you may ſurely eaſily find it; but if you cannot find it, or any thing like it, then you may be ſure it is not the the Doctrine of the Church, though it may be the Doctrine Preach'd of late in the Churches, and then you will have occaſion to follow the Apoſtle's advice, which is, not to have the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Men in Admiration, and to remember what our Lord often incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
<pb facs="tcp:96576:3"/>to his Diſciples, to beware <hi>whom,</hi> and <hi>how</hi> they heard. There are ſome times in which his advice is more needful than others; and this, I think, is ſuch a time, when our Church-men are divided in their Practice, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome practical Points; and whether the greater or ſmaller number is in the Right, you will never be able judge, though it concerns your Souls to judge aright, unleſs you will hear what both ſay.</p>
            <p>There are Men of equal Eminence and Learning on both ſides, and if one ſide can pretend the Advantage Numbers, the other can urge againſt it the intereſt of ſaving, and getting more, to depretiate the Number and Authority of their Examples, together with a multiform variety of moſt different Opinions, and Principles among them; one of them complying in one ſenſe, and upon one Principle, and another upon another.</p>
            <p>This Book of mine is a ſhort and ſummary Apology for the little ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Number, againſt the Arguments and Accuſations of the Arch-Biſhop, who is now at the head of the other Party; and if it can prevail with you to look more narrowly into the Controverſie, in which you have enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Grace, I ſhall think my ſelf ſufficiently recompenced for my little Pains in Writing of it; and in Hopes that you, or ſome of you, who have moſt leiſure and ingenuity, will do ſo, I Subſcribe in all Sincerity,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Faithful, and Humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96576:3"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGY FOR THE New Separation.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Once had the Happineſs to hear you preach an excellent Sermon in which you ſpoke many excellent <hi>things that were true and juſt,</hi> with all that ſerious Air and Authority that could become a ſincere Preacher, I often had occaſion ſince to wiſh it had been put in Print; it was preached at St. <hi>Margaret's Weſtminſter,</hi> on the 30th of <hi>January</hi> was two years, before the Gentlemen of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention,</hi> and remembring the excellent Diſcourſe you then made, and preſſed upon the Conſciences of the <hi>Conventioners,</hi> I had a great Deſire and Curioſity to read your late <hi>fare-well Sermon,</hi> to ſee if you ſtood firm in theſe times of Defection to your former Principles: But to be plain and ſerious with you, I find you ſo altered, like many of your Brethren, from your ſelf, that though Dr. <hi>Sharpe</hi> is ſtill the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet I do not find that the <hi>Dead</hi> of <hi>Norwich</hi> and the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> are the ſame Man: For then, my Lord, you preach'd with great appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Zeal and Sincerity <hi>againſt the reſiſting and depoſing Doctrines;</hi> for which you had the Honour to be cenſured by many of the <hi>Houſe;</hi> but now in the very Phraſe and Language of thoſe Authors who have taught the World thoſe damnable Doctrines,<note place="margin">Page 30:</note> you tell us that <hi>we muſt be more concerned for our Countrey and Nation, than the Intereſt of any ſingle Man in it;</hi> A Saying certainly in the ſenſe you muſt needs mean it, fitter for a Biſhop of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> than the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, which, conformably to our Laws, and the eternal Reaſons of them, teacheth her Children, That <hi>the Intereſt of the People is wrapt up with the Safety and Intereſt of the Prince, and that they can never be happy without him.</hi> This our Anceſtors have often felt, and confeſſed upon Experience, particularly Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> in his Preface to <hi>Cotton's Abridgment,</hi> to whoſe Words I refer you: But you, my Lord, contrary to all Law, Reaſon, and Experience, have taught the People in this Sermon to ſet up a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate and diſtinct Intereſt againſt that of the Prince, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to reſiſt or depoſe him, to turn or keep him out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96576:4"/>be he who he will, even the preſent, as well as any of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Kings.</p>
            <p>You cannot but know that there are a party of Men among us, who are more concerned for <hi>another Intereſt</hi> than the Intereſt of the King, I mean the <hi>Comman wealthſmen,</hi> and they thinking that Intereſt; which I aſſure you is a growing Intereſt, the Intereſt of their Countrey; they may upon your Principles do as much for his Majeſty as the Pretenders of <hi>Publick Good</hi> in former Ages have done by ſome of his Royal Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, if they can but once perſuade the People, who are eaſily decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or a conſiderable number of them, that it is not for the Intereſt of the Nation that he ſhould longer reign over them. The leaſt the People ſo perſuaded would probaly ſay of their Majeſties in a time of general defection would be in the Words of Dr. <hi>Sherlock, Let them go, if they cannot defend-themſelves;</hi> and when they were gone, (which all their faithfull Subjects pray God to forbid,) they would think it their Duty to ſhut the door after them; for you, and ſuch as you, would preſently exhort them to <hi>ſtudy to be quiet, and doe their own buſineſs; and to be more concerned for their Countrey and Nation, than</hi> [to break the Peace of] <hi>for the Intereſt of any ſingle Man,</hi> or Woman in it, as their Majeſties would then be ſtyled. Nay, this great Concern of yours for our Country and Nation, in oppoſition to the Intereſt of the Prince, will juſtifie any thing as well as being quiet or ſitting ſtill. It expoſes him to <hi>Ehud</hi>'s Dagger, as well as <hi>Gideon</hi>'s Sword, to Aſſaſſins and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voes, as well as to Rebels, Depoſers, and High Courts of Juſtice, for a Prince in your Arithmetick is but a <hi>ſingle Man,</hi> and if his Safety and <hi>Intereſt</hi> is not in Reality or Opinion conſiſtent with that of the People, they may diſpatch or depoſe him any way, it matters not how, a <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villiac</hi> or a <hi>Clement</hi> may doe the Work with a Steletto, when a League or Aſſociation cannot doe it. Princes at this rate can be no longer ſafe than they continue in the good opinion of the People,<note place="margin">Page 29.</note> 
               <hi>and are looked upon to be good Men, and encouragers of true Religion.</hi> As long as the Caſe is ſo, you ſay, they <hi>are not onely to be ſubmitted to, bus to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged as Bleſſings:</hi> But by the Rule of Contraries, If they come to be, or, which is all one, happen to be thought bad Men by the People, and Encouragers of falſe Religion, as <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the 1ſt of <hi>England</hi> were, then they are no longer to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged as Bleſſings, but to be reſiſted, depoſed or murthered as Curſes, and no Man ought to be concerned at it, but to be quiet, and let the Deliverers of the People doe their Word their own way; for as you intimate the King is but a ſingle Man, and the Intereſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey which others call the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> is to be preferred without Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception before the Intereſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> before the Welfare and ſafety of any Particular Man.</p>
            <p>I profeſs, my Lord, I cannot but wonder that any Government ſhould prefer Men that turn Subjects to it upon ſuch looſe and dangerous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, as are equally deſtructive of all Governments, and can ſecure none: For this Doctrine upon which your Exhortation is founded; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermines Senates, as well as Kings; for as a King, my Lord, is with you but a ſingle Man; ſo by the ſame figure in Politicks, Senates are but a few ſingle Men met together, and ſo the People in parity of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96576:4"/>ought at all times to be more concerned for their Countrey than a ſew ſingle Men. Nay, my Lord, by this Doctrine the minor Part, in a pure Democracy, can never want a plauſible pretence of reſiſting the major, in whoſe Determinations they ought to acquieſce; for though they are the <hi>minor,</hi> they may always pretend to be a <hi>ſounder</hi> Part, that are more concerned for their Countrey than for the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of any num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Men, though never ſo great; and ſo at this rate there can be no Peace in any Nation or Government, but eternal Oppoſition without a powerful ſtanding Army, which is an uncertain ſtate of Peace; a Peace as long as it endures attended with Oppreſſion; Poverty, and Slavery, and not much better for the People than a State of War. Nay, my Lord, you will find that this Principle of yours will ruine Biſhops as well as Kings; for when Sir <hi>George Mackenzy,</hi> and others of the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Party, defended the Biſhops of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the Convention of that Kingdom, <hi>What a doe,</hi> ſaid a Presbyterian Lord, <hi>is here about the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, I think we ought to be more concerned for our Countrey than the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Twelve Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was of ſuch Latitude as this of yours, and ſuch Latitudinarians as you are, that Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> complained, not long before he had taken the Oaths, had ruined both the Church and State. He then ſaw how ſuch looſe Doctrines as yours made them both Ohnoxious to an everlaſting rotation of Turns and Revolutions, and was not ſparing in his Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Invectives upon one whom he thought the <hi>Arth-Latitudina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian;</hi> but as Dr. <hi>Collins</hi> ſaid, at <hi>Cambridge—Then was then, but now is now;</hi> for ſince that he hath left the narrow for the wide and eaſie Way, or it I may compare Principles, as you do Religion to Cloaths,<note place="margin">Page 14.</note> he hath changed his old ſtreight uneaſie Faſhion, for the never eaſie Mode; he hath caſt off the ſlaviſh Principles of ſtrict and <hi>inflexible Loyalty</hi> to his Prince, his Soul is no longer fettered with them, but is as free as the happy Liberty of Obeying and <hi>Regnant Powers</hi> can make him. It mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not with you or him, my Lord, what the King be, lawful or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, real or titular, rightful or wrongful, provided he be in Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Throne. Thus let Twenty Kings ſupplant one another, and you can transfer you: Allegiance to the later, though you have recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized and ſworn Allegiance never ſo ſolemnly to the former, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Power can abſolve you from that Oath, nay though you have made a <hi>vow to God</hi> of Obedience to him, and he actually claims his Right, and proſecutes his Claim, and charges his Subject, to keep their Allegiance entire for him; yet notwithſtanding all this you can turn Subjects to him that uſurps his Throne, though he got it and keep it never ſo unjuſtly. like the Gentleman's Spaniel, who forſook his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and followed the Thief, after he had knocked him down and got upon his Horſe.</p>
            <p>Thus with you, and ſuch as you, my Lord, whoever can mount <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephalus</hi> will be your <hi>Alexander,</hi> whoever can get into the Throne ſhall certainly be your <hi>Caeſar;</hi> if God ſhould ſuffer a <hi>Cromwell</hi> to deſtroy their Majeſties, and ſeize the Crown, you would own him and be Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to him, and pray publickly for him in the Regal Style, becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſaid, That every Soul muſt be ſubject,<note place="margin">Page 28.</note> 
               <hi>and hath bad us put up Prayers, and Supplications, and Interceſſions for all Men, eſpecially
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96576:5"/>for Kings, and all that are in Authority, without any diſtinction or reſtriction what Kings, or what Perſons in Authority we are to pray for, and what not:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe Words, my Lord, I preſume to conjecture upon what Principles you took the Oath; for being asked in Company ſome time ſince why you did not write a Book to perſuade men to take the <hi>New Oath,</hi> you replied to this effect, That you believed you could write Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactorily upon the Subject; but you were afraid <hi>the Government would not like your Reaſons;</hi> and in truth, my Lord, you had reaſon for what you ſaid; for no Government can like this time-ſerving and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious Principle of ſwearing Allegiance unto Princes. Indeed a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Government may connive at it in a time of Exigence, but it can never approve it; it may be content with it upon Force, when it can have Allegiance paid upon no better terms; but when it grows ſtrong enough it will deſpiſe ſuch beggarly Elements of Subjection, being the Anthers of then, to condign Puniſhment, and order their Books to be burnt by the hand of the Common Hang-man.</p>
            <p>For my own part I am not afraid to tell your Grace, that I hope to ſee ſuch Biſhop and Prieſts become Baſe and Contemptible, in the Eyes Loth of King and People, that expound St. <hi>Paul</hi> as you and Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> have done, contrary to the Rules of moral Equity and Juſtice, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Allegiance to the Government upon a Principle that is deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to it, and the true and laſting Peace of the Kingdom in which our Happineſs does conſiſt. No Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> but you and Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> and a few more ſince the Revolution, ever ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 11.1, 2. and I have ſo good Opinion of the Conſtancy of our Clergy to their Principles, that I verily believe were your Expoſition propoſed to the Convocation, they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it as contrary to right Reaſon, and the moral Duties of Religion, acording to which all the general and unlimitted Precepts in the Goſpel concerning <hi>relative Duties,</hi> ought to be limitted and underſtood. Doth not Nature it ſelf, at firſt hearing, teach us that the Apoſtle by <hi>higher Powers</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> in thoſe two places, meant rightful <hi>higher Powers</hi> and <hi>Kings?</hi> And will not you your ſelf grant, that in other places where he, or other Apoſtles exhorts, Children to obey their Parents, Wives to obey their Husbands, Servants their Maſters, and the People their Paſtors. that he me us only ſuch as are truly and rightfully ſo, though according to you own Obſervation, <hi>He makes no reſtriction, or diſtinction</hi> what Father, Husbands, Maſters and Paſtors, <hi>are to be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and what not?</hi> But you imply that the reaſon of this Exhortation to pray for Kings is general; and are not the Reaſons as general upon which he exhorts us to perform our relative Duties of our other Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, as hath been obſerved in the ſeveral learned Anſwers to Dr <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock?</hi> to which I humbly refer <hi>your Grace</hi> for your better information in the following Order, as I have read them with great Delight and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: <hi>The Title of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>jurper after a through Settelement examined,</hi> p. 39 <hi>and forwards. The Duty of Alleg ance ſettled upon its true Grounds according to Scripture and Reaſon,</hi> Chap. 3. <hi>Dr.</hi> Sherlock <hi>'s Caſe of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance conſidered,</hi> Sect. 3. <hi>The Examination of the Arguments drawn from Scripture and Reaſon, in Dr.</hi> Sherlock's <hi>Caſe of Allegiance; in the Examination of</hi> Sect. 4. Pag. 28</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96576:5"/>
            <p>I have taken upon me to direct your Grace to theſe particular places, in hopes that you will read them, and impartially examine the Reaſon of theſe learned Anthours againſt Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s way of Expounding the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. and by conſequence againſt your own, who after this manner have expounded the Apoſtle's Precept of Praying for Kings, in a Senſe as unlimitted, as he hath done the other of Subjection to them; <hi>viz.</hi> of Praying for Kings without diſtinction, provided they are in Poſſeſſion of the Throne.</p>
            <p>Theſe Expoſitions, my Lord, as ſome Men think, reflect upon their Majeſties and the Acts of Recognition; and if you have no more to ſay to juſtifie your Praying for them, <hi>Exaltabunt Jacebei,</hi> the Adverſaries, I fear, will have occaſion to triumph.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I could name ſome great Men among you, who when they were directed to read ſome of <hi>their Books,</hi> replied that they <hi>were ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and deſired not to be unſettled,</hi> but I expect better things from a Perſon of your Candour and Ingenuity: Nay, my Lord, I think you are bound in Honour and Conſcience, to examine your Adverſaries Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt the unlimitted Senſe of the Apoſtle's Exhortations, for fear you ſhould happen to be in the wrong, and continue to delude the People by an Expoſition of his Words apparently contrary to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of natural Reaſon, and by conſequence to the meaning of that holy Spirit by which the Apoſtle wrote.</p>
            <p>You cannot but know that this <hi>unlimitted</hi> Senſe, in which you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the Apoſtle, is of <hi>ill Fame,</hi> and hath been generally diſappro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the learned Divines of our Church; it was inſiſted on it the times of the late Uſurpation by Phanatical time-ſerving Writers, but rejected with diſdain by the Martyrs and Confeſſors of Loyalty among the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Clergy-men, as it now is by <hi>Jacobeans.</hi> It was ſo expounded by Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> who in the late Uſurpation argued for Subjection, as Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> doth now, and was ever after Infamous for it, and expoſed without Mercy for it by your old Acquaintance Dr. <hi>Grove,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> as you may ſee in the Margent.<note n="‡" place="margin">Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi>'s Farewell Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>p. 15.</hi> It is a moſt excellent Preſertative againſt <hi>Tower-hill.</hi> But what is this famed Poſition of the Doctor's? As far as I can learn it was laid down in theſe very Words, or to this purpoſe, <hi>Regimen Politicum fundatur in Provident à D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i Extraordinarià.</hi>
                  <p>This Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> calls his aſſerting Providential Diſpoſal, though one might conjecture what this means, yet it had not been ſo clear without the Comment, which he has made upon it in the beginning of his humble Petition to the Supreme Authority, the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England;</hi> in ſhort it is this: That whoever they be that get the Power into their hands, the Providence of God evidently appears in removing others, and inveſting them with the Government, <hi>And he looks upon it as his Duty to yield to this Authority all active and chearful Obedience, even for Conſcience ſake.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is a fine pleable Principle as a Man can wiſh, 'twill lap about your Finger like <hi>Barbary</hi> Gold. Thus when King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of bleſſed Memory, had the Power in his hands, this was an <hi>Extraordinary Providence,</hi> and the Right of Government was in him: But ſtay, it may be the Dector had not ſtudied the point ſo ſoon. but to be ſure when the Parliament got the better, that was an Extraordinary Providence ideed, and then indeed without doubt they were the Supreme Authority, as this Petitioner ſtyles them; and ſo was <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> and ſo was <hi>Richard,</hi> and ſo was the <hi>Rump,</hi> and ſo was the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96576:6"/>of Safety,</hi> and ſo was I know not who, and ſo round until his Majeſties moſt happy Reſtauration; and then becauſe there was an <hi>Extraordinary Providence</hi> in that, ſo is he too, and ſo Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> is as good a Subject as can be deſired, and ſo he had been whoever had come. And thus if the <hi>Turk</hi> ſhould happen to over-run the Kingdom of <hi>Poland,</hi> and deliver the People from Popiſh Tyranny, this were an <hi>Extraordinary Providence,</hi> and the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> would preſently became the lawful Sovereign of that Realm, and that (which the proud <hi>Mahometan</hi> little thinks) by virtue of a <hi>Poſition</hi> made at <hi>Cambridge</hi> above Twenty Years ago.</p>
                  <p>I have conſidered it as well as I am able, and cannot make the Doctor's <hi>Providentia Extraordinaria</hi> to ſignifie any more in effect, than what they call Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s <hi>Potentia Irreſiſtibilis,</hi> and then the Doctor, and he, and our Author, have been the only Three, for ought I know, that have perfectly agreed in <hi>this uncouth,</hi> and <hi>'till of late unheard of Point,</hi> that unſettles the Foundations of the Earth, and gives a liberty to every bold-<hi>Uſurper</hi> that invades the Crown, at leaſt legimates his Claim, if he can be but Succeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful enough to place it on his own Head.</p>
                  <p>But Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> muſt know, that though this aſſertion be a good Expedient to ſecure ones Neck under an illegal and tyrannical Power, yet it never can make him a faithful Subject to his natural and lawful Prince; or <hi>it robs him of Title, which he hath by Inheritance,</hi> and juſtifies every thing by Event onely. It adds Affliction to the Miſery of unfortunate Kings, <hi>and flatters the proſperous Traitor, as if he were the Darling of Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, you cannot but be conſcious to your ſelf, that two Years ago you were not of opinion, at leaſt you were not fully perſuaded, that the Text allowed us to pray in behalf of a King <hi>de Facto</hi> againſt the King <hi>de Jure,</hi> or in behalf of a King in Poſſeſſion againſt the legal King, as you and Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> ſtill acknowledge King <hi>James</hi> to be, though he is out of Poſſeſſion; or, elſe why did you at his Houſe, in the <hi>Temple,</hi> expreſs ſo much diſlike and diſſatisfaction at the Prayers in the Office of the firſt general Faſt: But the World is ſince well mended with you, and what was matter of Difficulty to you then is no: ſo now; for ſince that time you have better Studied the great Apoſtle at <hi>Canterbury</hi> than you did at <hi>Norwich,</hi> and plainly diſcovered that he is, and always was for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ppermoſt,</hi> and directs us to pay our Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance and Devotion, without enquiring into Titles, to the King in the Throne.</p>
            <p>I wiſh for the Honour of our Religion, and the better Settlement of the Nation, that theſe Notions had ſtill remained among thoſe <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> and not obtained admiſſion within the pale of the Church, more eſpecially I wiſh, for the Honour of the <hi>holy Order,</hi> that they had never been taught in Pulpits, at leaſt by our Biſhops and Dignified Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who are the more conſpicuous Lights, and upon whom the Reputation of the Clergy depends. Certainly, my Lord, ſuch <hi>inſecure</hi> Doctrines to Princes, when once they come to underſtand them, cannot be very acceptable to them, nor can they much value ſuch <hi>Protean</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as will how the Knee to them to day, and do the ſame to their greateſt Enemies to morrow, if they can get into their Thrones I doubt not but <hi>their Majeſties,</hi> when they have leiſure to reflect, will be ſenſible how much ſuch Men impoſe upon them, and how little Security they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96576:6"/>have in their Allegiance, though they pretend to transfer it all unto them, becauſe it is a temporary and a moveable Allegiance, which they can transfer <hi>in infinitum,</hi> and vear backwards and forwards, or come about to every point of the Compaſs, like the Weather-cocks upon their Church ſteeples, as the Wind ſhall blow. My Lord, one <hi>Jacobite,</hi> cou'd he turn to <hi>their Majeſties</hi> upon his own Principles, would be worth an hundred ſuch Subjects as you and Dr. <hi>Sherlock;</hi> and whenever <hi>Providence</hi> ſhall remove the Obſtacles which lie in the way of their <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance</hi> to them, they will have reaſon to value them as ſo many Jewels of their Crown.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I cannot deny but that I like the Converſation of the Men, cauſe they are Men of Conſcience, and Honour, and diſcourſe, and write like Scholars and Chriſtians, though Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> calls then little Writers; this makes me keep Company with them, and ſo I do with ſome Men of Parts among the <hi>Republicans,</hi> and ſo I would do with <hi>Ariſtotle, Plato,</hi> and <hi>Socrates,</hi> were they alive, and ſee how they liked your Principle of tying <hi>Allegiance to actual Adminiſtration.</hi> I will not tell you what they ſay of you at <hi>Richards,</hi> for I am afraid it might ruffle your ſmooth Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to let you know how unmercifully thoſe Gentlemen tear your Rocket without any regard to your venerable Character, but the <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites</hi> are more reſpectful to it upon Principle; and I will ſpend the reſt of my Time and Paper in letting you know what they reply to every thing you have ſaid againſt them, from the 25th Page to the end of your Sermon, in which you have expoſed them as on a Stage, firſt to your Pariſh, and then to the whole Kingdom.</p>
            <p>They obſerve then, my Lord,<note place="margin">Page 26.</note> that you might have exhorted your People <hi>to ſtudy Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and endeavour in their ſeveral Stations to promote the publick Tranquillity,</hi> without pointing at them as diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it; and they ſay they have reaſon to think that you have done it, with a deſign to provoke both the Government and People againſt them, and to that end they ſuſpect it is that you repreſent them as a <hi>Faction,</hi> more eſpecially as a <hi>Faction in Religion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 29.</note> and tell the World they ground their <hi>Faction on a State-point,</hi> or, as you afterwards explain your ſelf, <hi>upon a mere State point.</hi> This, my Lord, is the great Charge you draw up againſt them; and they pretend that it is none of the things of your Text, as being neither <hi>True, Honeſt,</hi> nor <hi>Juſt;</hi> and they wonder they could be ſo falſly charged by a learned Man, who can diſtinguiſh very well, though common Readers and Hearers cannot, betwixt a <hi>State-point,</hi> and <hi>a mere point of State.</hi> Theſe two things they ſay are very different, though you fallaciouſly confound them together, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they diſtinguiſh betwixt a <hi>State-point,</hi> which is purely <hi>ſuch,</hi> and a <hi>State-point</hi> which happens alſo to be a point of Morality or practical Religion, and in its Nature affects the Conſciences of Men. As for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample— The <hi>Spaniſh Match,</hi> ſay they, in the time of <hi>James the Firſt,</hi> was a State point, <hi>i.e.</hi> a mere State-point, which, had it been ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, could not have obliged any Man in Conſcience (though the Clergy preached againſt it) to refuſe Communion with the Church, or Subjection to the State. The <hi>Vote of Non-addreſſing</hi> was alſo a <hi>State-point;</hi> but then ſay they, not a <hi>mere State-point,</hi> but ſuch an one as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96576:7"/>was withall a matter of Morality, which many of the Members thought in their Conſciences a great breach of their Duty to concur with, and therefore left the Houſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, my Lord, they appeal to you, and the whole <hi>Caſuiſtical</hi> World, if a <hi>Safe point,</hi> and more particularly a point of Government or Policy, may not become a <hi>Caſe of Conſcience</hi> in a Kingdom, as well as in a Family, College, or Dioceſe; and whether Queſtions about Right and Wrong, Lawful and Unlawful, Juſt and Unjuſt, may not happen to ariſe in a <hi>Point,</hi> or Act of State, as well as in other practical Points?</p>
            <p>Was not the <hi>Engagement</hi> a State-point in thoſe times? And did not the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> make a Caſe of Conſcience of it, and choſe many of them to ſuffer rather than to take it, becauſe they thought the matter of it Sinful? Was it not a State-point with the Loyal Nobility, Gentry, and Clergy, whether they ſhould turn Liege-ſubject, to <hi>Oliver?</hi> And yet becauſe it was not a <hi>mere State-point,</hi> but ſuch an one as touched their Conſciences, they choſe to be ſequestred rather than ſin in cloſing with the Uſurpers, and transfer their Allegiance from the King to whom they thought it due: The Clergy alſo then ſet up ſeparate Meetings from the Churches, and Private Worſhip in oppoſition to the Publick, in many places of the Kingdom, as Dr. <hi>Wild</hi> and Dr. <hi>Gunning</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Fell</hi> in <hi>Oxon;</hi> for then they thought it was not the <hi>Place,</hi> or the <hi>Numbers,</hi> but the <hi>Cauſe</hi> that made the Separation a Schiſme; and the <hi>Jacobites</hi> in like manner think (how truly I ſhall not now diſpute) that they have juſt Cauſe of Separation given them, and that therefore their Separation is no Schiſm. The New Oath of Allegiance which you intimate to be a <hi>mere State-point,</hi> they think withall to be a great Point of Religion, in which the Intereſts of Truth, Juſtice, and moral Honeſty are concerned, and they verily believe they cannot take it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breaking three or four of the Commandments, which they think to be as ſacred in themſelves, and as dear to God that made them, as any Articles in the <hi>Creed:</hi> For the ſame Reaſon they profeſs they cannot join in the Prayers as they ſtand altered, nor with the additional Prayers; and to ſpeak my own Judgment, I think no Party of Men ever made a more plauſible Apology or Defence for themſelves, than is made for them in a Book called <hi>Chriſtian Prudence,</hi> to which I refer your <hi>Grace,</hi> and I dare ſay you will not think your Pains ill ſpent in reading of it, if you pleaſe to peruſe it with a free and unprejudicate Mind.</p>
            <p>But, my Lord, beſides that which you call a <hi>State-point,</hi> there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a <hi>Church-point,</hi> of which you take no notice, though it be another known Cauſe of their Separation, and that is the putting of New Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops into the Thrones of the Old ones, whoſe Deprivation they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be <hi>null</hi> and <hi>unjuſt,</hi> and give ſuch Reaſons for it, as the tender Regard I have for the Government, and theſe Eraſtian Times will not ſuffer me to recite. I have urged the Authority of the <hi>Baroccian Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript</hi> againſt them; but to that they anſwer many ways very well, and, which troubles me not a little, they aſſure from their Friends at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Hody</hi> hath not printed the whole Manuſcript, but omitted a <hi>Collection of Canons,</hi> which immediately follows where he left off, written in the ſame Hand, which ſhews that the Author is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96576:7"/>of Synodical Deprivations; and if this be ſo indeed, as I fear it is, then I muſt ſay, that Mr. <hi>Hody</hi> hath not ſtrictly kept his<note n="‡" place="margin">Jam ad alia, Lector, procedas; at priuſquam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedas, Votorum quorundam mihi teſtis eſto; &amp; olim, ſi unquam violavero, Monitor; Vo torum quorundam eruditis Viris, proh dolor! hucuſque ignotorum; ſed quae ego pertetuò à primis literis, ut facio, feci ex Corde:
<q>
                     <l>Faxit Numen,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t vel aeterno ego ſilentio inter non ſcribentes deliteſeam,</l>
                     <l>Vel ſemper, ut virum ingenuum, liberalis ac generoſae Educationis,</l>
                     <l>Veraeque Philoſopiae ſtudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſum decet, ſcribam:</l>
                     <l>Verita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is unicae Indagator,</l>
                     <l>Abſique omni Styli Acerbitate,</l>
                     <l>Mitis, urbanus, candidus,</l>
                     <l>Ad id quod indecens eſt adeo non pronus, ut nec movendus,</l>
                     <l>Nugarum demque Contemptor.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>I do not know whether <hi>Ger. Joh.</hi> and <hi>Iſaac Voſſius, Uther</hi> and <hi>Dodwell,</hi> ever made ſuch a Vow; but this I dare ſay, if they had printed this <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Manuſcript, they would have had ſo much Ingenuity as to have printed the whole, at leaſt to have given Reaſons to the World why they did not.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, my Lord, you ſee that the Non-compliance and Separation of our <hi>New Nonconformiſts</hi> is not grounded upon a <hi>mere State point;</hi> ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther merely upon a Point of State, and they think they have R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to expect ſatisfaction from your <hi>Grace,</hi> not onely for wrong aſſigning one Cauſe of their <hi>Separation,</hi> but alſo for not aſſigning both. I confeſs their Opinion is dreadfull in its conſequence, as being like to involve all the Nation except themſelves in Schiſm, and I have been ſo free as to tell them of it, and alſo prayed them to conſider what an <hi>Odium</hi> they will bring upon themſelves by it; but to that they ſay, they cannot hinder the Conſequences of things, and wiſhed me to conſide, That as a Nation, or Province, may fall into <hi>Indolatry, Rebellion,</hi> or <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> ſo alſo into <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and that our Nation fell into the firſt of thoſe Sins in the time of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> into the ſecond and third in the time of the <hi>Rump</hi> and <hi>Cron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>well,</hi> and if they now charge it with the fourth Sin, it is no more than what your Grace, and your complying Brethren do for <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the ſame Apology they think will ſerve for both, though of the two they acknowledge the Scottiſh to be the more grievous Schiſm.</p>
            <p>Thus much, my Lord, I have ſaid by way of Enquiry into the Grounds of the Separation of the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> to acquit them from the Charge of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Schiſm, I now come to your Reflections, which they ſay are as unjuſt as your Charge, and as groundleſs and impertinent as it. You re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them in p. 26. as Men <hi>that have different Notions about Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and framers of Hypotheſes about Government.</hi> To which they reply, That if you mean that their Notions of Politicks are different from yours, that they confeſs to be true; but if you mean that their Notions about Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks are different from the true Engliſh Polity, or antient Government of this Kingdom, or that they frame any other <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> about it, than what the Law hath framed; this they deny, and deſire all the World to take notice, That they are by Principle ſo far from making <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſes</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96576:8"/>againſt the Government of <hi>England,</hi> or Alterations in it, that they ſuffer both as <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> for their ſtrict adherence to it, and that you are the Men that have different Notions of <hi>Politicks,</hi> from the National Polity or Conſtitution, and that you have actually framed ſix or ſeven <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> about Government, as different from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as from the Law it ſelf.</p>
            <p>For the truth of this they appeal to your own Writings, out of which they intend to collect ſuch notorious Schemes of State-Notions, and Doctrines of Politicks, that <hi>they that dwell on the Earth ſhall won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at them,</hi> as at the Beaſt in the <hi>Revelations, when they behold them.</hi> One of them, as I am told, hath been at the pains to compare Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>'s Notions about Politicks with thoſe of <hi>Julian Johnſon</hi>'s, and can make it appear from that Collation, that <hi>Julian</hi> is much the better Church-man, and the more Orthodox <hi>Apoſtate</hi> of the two. In ſhort, my Lord, in anſwer to this Reflexion upon them, as Coiners of <hi>Nations about Politicks,</hi> they ſtick not to ſay, that you are the <hi>Statiſts</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lincians,</hi> who with your <hi>humane Policies</hi> have corrupted your Religion, defiled the Prieſthood, diſhonoured the Church, ſcandalized her Friends, and cauſed her Enemies to triumph.</p>
            <p>In the next Paragraph you ſay, That <hi>it is very grievous for thoſe that promote a Separation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 27.</note> 
               <hi>who have always declared themſelves Friends to the Church, and Enemies to Schiſm.</hi> To this Reflexion they reply, That they are ſtill as much Friends of the Church, and Enemies of Schiſm, as ever; but then by the Church they underſtand the <hi>True Old Church of</hi> England, with all her venerable Doctrines of Faith, Juſtice, and moral Honeſty, and all her ſtrict Decrees againſt the <hi>reſiſting, depoſing,</hi> and <hi>forferting</hi> Doctrines; the Church of <hi>England</hi> with all her plain Primitive Doctrines of Chriſtian Honeſty and Simplicity, againſt <hi>Equivocations</hi> and <hi>Mental Reſervations;</hi> the Church that always abhorred <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Perjury,</hi> as well as <hi>Idolatry;</hi> that never allowed her Children <hi>to do any moral Evil for a good End, or with a good Intention:</hi> In a word, the Church that equally condemus both the Parts of Popery, that which teaches us to be falſe to Men, as well as that which is injurious to God; that which pollutes our Morals, as well as that which pollutes our Faith and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. This pure Virgin Church, which they think is now driven once more into the Wilderneſs, they ſay is the Church which they adhere to, and to which they think you ought to have adhered with them, and that you have ſeparated from her, and them, and not they from you: For they ſay, they are juſt where they were when you were laſt with them, and have not budged a Foot ſince from that Church, and that you cannot ſay they have broken from you, unleſs you will affirm that when a Ship breaks from the Shoar where ſhe lay at Anchor, the Shoar removes from her, and not ſhe from the Shoar.</p>
            <p>And then as to the next Reflexion, of <hi>being diſtaſted at the eſtabliſht Worſhip, for which they were zealous before,</hi> they ſay they are as zealous for it as ever, as far as the <hi>Matter of the Prayers is the ſame;</hi> but the Matter of ſome of the old Prayers they ſay is changed, and this Matter, with that of all the New ones, being the ſubject Matter of the New Oath of Allegiance, they have the ſame difficulty of Conſcience upon them, as to ſaying of theſe, as taking of thoſe: Wherefore, in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96576:8"/>to your fallacious Queſtion about the Liturgie and Prayers, they deſire to know if you put the Queſtion of the whole Liturgie, and all the Prayers in it, or not: If not, then the Queſtion is not to your purpoſe; but if you indeed mean the whole Liturgy, and all the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in it, as you would be underſtood, then, they ſay, they muſt tell you that the Liturgy and Prayers are not the ſame they were, and by conſequence, that the Propoſition implied in your Queſtion is falſe: For as Changing the Name of God for the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> in the <hi>invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> part of any Collect in the Liturgy, would change the Object of Worſhip, and make it not as it was, a Prayer to God, but to the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin; ſo changing the Name of a Man for that of his Enemy, in the <hi>petitionary</hi> part of any Collect, makes it quite another Prayer, not for the Man as it was before the Change of Names, but for his Enemy; and by conſequence, alteration of Names alters the Matter and Intention of the Prayer, and makes it as different from it ſelf, as the two Men and their Intereſts happen to be. They ſuppoſe, that if a Man ſhould raze the Names out of a Petition to their Majeſties, and put the French King's Name in their place, that it would no longer be a Petition to them, but to their mortal Enemy; and therefore in Reply to the next Queſtion which follows about the <hi>ſame Liturgie,</hi> they ſay, this change of Names has changed the Prayers in the Liturgie, and that this change diſguſts their Conſciences, and helps to drive them from your Churches, being one cauſe of their Separation from the Publick, and but one; for as I juſt now ſhewed your Grace, there was another, of which you were pleaſed to take no notice.</p>
            <p>Ay, but you ſay, <hi>they proceed ſo far as to declare open War, and ſet up ſeparate Congregations in oppoſition to the publick.</hi> To this they ſay, for the foreſaid Reaſons, That they did not begin this ſpiritual War, which on their ſide is purely <hi>Defenſive,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>driven</hi> from the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and that the ſame Reaſons that will juſtifie their Separation from it, will alſo juſtifie ſetting up ſeparate Meetings in oppoſition to it, in which they think the pure Church of <hi>England,</hi> with her pure Worſhip, may be ſeen and heard like the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in the firſt perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Chriſtianity, in the upper rooms. And in reply to the great Emphaſis, which, to ſupply the want of Argument, you put upon Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating from the <hi>Publick,</hi> and Setting up Congregations in oppoſition to the <hi>Publick,</hi> they pray you to conſider, That the Multitude, or great Majority which uſually makes the <hi>Publick,</hi> is often in the wrong. You will not deny but the Multitude or Publick are now the Schiſmaticks in <hi>Scotland;</hi> they were ſo under the Donatiſt Biſhops in <hi>Africk;</hi> they were ſo in <hi>England</hi> under the Popiſh <hi>Marian</hi> Biſhops; they were ſo under <hi>Aaron</hi> in the buſineſs of the Calf; they were ſo in <hi>Iſrael</hi> under <hi>Ahab</hi> and the Idolatrous Prieſts; and, laſtly, they were ſo under the <hi>Arian</hi> Emperours and Biſhops, throughout the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. In ſhort, my Lord, they ſay when the Publick is in the right, and gives no juſt cauſe of ſeparating from it, that then it is a great Sin, to ſet up private Meetings againſt it; but when it is in the wrong, and gives juſt cauſe of ſeparating, it then becomes innocent, and a Duty to doe ſo, though the <hi>Publick</hi> be in Poſſeſſion of all the Churches, as it uſually is, when Safety, Honour, and Riches attend the erring ſide.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96576:9"/>
            <p>I hope by this time, my Lord, you underſtand <hi>what their Meaning is in Setting up ſeparate Congregations;</hi> for it is the Cauſe, and not the local Churches and Revenues that make, ſay they, a true Church; and therefore, in Anſwer to your Queſtion, they pray your Grace to conſider, that Men <hi>that have been branders of Schiſm,</hi> may think it not onely innocent, but their Duty to ſeparate from the Publick, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, without changing their Principles. Nay, ſometimes their Principles, unleſs they can change them, will oblige them to doe ſo, though they do not think <hi>Schiſm can change its Nature;</hi> and this they think is their own Caſe; and therefore they challenge you, and the whole Regnant Church of <hi>England,</hi> with all the advantage if its Churches and Revenues, but more particularly the <hi>Intruders,</hi> as they do not ſtick to call them, and all their <hi>Electors</hi> and <hi>Conſecrators,</hi> to prove that their Separation is a Schiſm. All your Arguments about it are couched in a few trifling Queſtions, of which this that follows is a terrible one, <hi>Have we not the ſam: Government in Church and State that we formerly had?</hi> And they appeal to your Grace's Conſcience, upon ſecond Thoughts, and <hi>as you expect to be called to Account for the Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of your Anſiver at the dreadfull Tribunal of God,</hi> if we have the ſame Government we formerly had. Do you know of no Changes it hath undergone, which may reaſonably aflect the Mind of every true En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhman, as well as the Conſcience of a good Subject? Was there no ſubſtantial Reason for throwing the Word <hi>rightfull</hi> out of the New Oath of Allegiance? Or for the Declaration that ſo many made for the eaſe of their Conſciences at the taking of it? And do not many among you ſtill complain in private of the Alterations that the Revolution hath made in the Government, and wiſh them unmade again. You cannot but know, they ſay, that there are many <hi>Grumbletonians,</hi> and half Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents among you; and therefore they wonder with what Confidence you could put this Queſtion about the Government, as well as that about the Prayers.</p>
            <p>But they ſay your Queſtion is fallacious, becauſe it is not to be put about the Government but about the Governours, and they think you will not ſay, that they are the ſame. They alſo make ſome diſtinctions about Things and Titles, which I ſhall not here recite, becauſe, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, your Grace hath heard of them, and knows them to be very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial in Controverſies of Allegiance, of which Praying for the King, next to Fighting for him, is a principal part; and therefore they ſay that in conteſts about Crowns in Chriſtian Kingdoms, the Subjects at the peril of their Souls are bound to conſider for which of the conteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Princes it is their Duty to pray, as well as for which it is to fight.</p>
            <p>The next Queſtion to this, ſay they, is as little to the purpoſe, wherein you ask, <hi>Have we not the ſame Articles and Doctrines of Religion pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly owned, and profeſſed, and taught, without the leaſt alteration?</hi> To this they Anſwer, That there are many Doctrines relating to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trovertie between you and them, <hi>taught, licenſed,</hi> and <hi>allowed,</hi> which have been condemned by your Predeceſſors of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the late Uſurparion, and formerly, and of late cenſured by the famous Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and which they verily believe a free Convocation would yet cenſure, as contrary to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96576:9"/>ſuch as theſe are, the <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> the <hi>Depoſing,</hi> the <hi>Forfeiting</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, which are to be ſeen in your licenſed Tracts. The Doctrine in behalf of bare Poſſeſſion, that it gives a Right to a Crown, to which another King hath a legal Title, that will juſtifie a recuperative War; the Doctrine of Providence, and actual Adminiſtration, the Doctrine which makes War God's Court, and Victory his Sentence lately aſſerted by the Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph.</hi> The Doctrine of laying aſide Kings for <hi>Mocal Incapacity,</hi> and another fine Doctrine, that Force from what Cauſe ſoever will diſengage Subjects from their Oaths of Allegiance, and juſtifie their entring into contrary Obligations; and they appeal to your Grace's Conſcience, if theſe Doctrines, not to mention others, which uſed to be ſo much branded and decryed by our Divines in Popiſh and Presbyterian Writers, be Articles of our Religion, or Doctrines of the Church of <hi>England</hi>— and the Preaching and Printing theſe Doctrines with Allowance, not mentioning the Preferments Men have for Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, is an Argument, they ſay, that the Articles and Doctrines you ſpeak of are not owned, but diſowned, not profeſſed but ſuppreſſed; and that they are not taught ſo publickly as formerly, becauſe they are not pleaſing, and ſome Men you know do not love to teach diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Things, though they be <hi>true, lovely, honeſt,</hi> and <hi>juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſay you again, <hi>What Government is there in the World will not meet with ſuch Subjects that are not ſatisfied with it, and if that diſaffec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be a juſt Reaſon to break Communion with the Eſtabliſhed Church, what Ligaments have we to tie Chriſtians together?</hi> Here they ſay, my Lord, you couch a Fallacy, which it did not become your Grace to make for the diſſatisfaction of Subjects, or rather, if you pleaſe, of the People againſt any Government, is, they ſay, of two ſorts, <hi>one</hi> upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of want of a good Title in the Governours, and <hi>another</hi> upon the account of want of good Adminiſtration, and with reſpect to the later, they acknowledge, there are very few Governments, which have not in ſome meaſure diſſatisfied their Subjects, but this ſort of diſſatisfaction, they ſay, is very conſiſtent with Church Communion under any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, though the Church-men ſhould happen to favour the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adminiſtration, as ſometimes they chance to do.</p>
            <p>But then with reſpect to the former ſort of diſſatisfaction, which is upon a moral Account, they ſay, it becomes a juſt Reaſon to break off Communion with the Church, when an acknowledgment of Right in wrongful Governours, at whom they are ſo diſſatisfied, is made a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or part of the Communion in the Prayers, and Sacraments of the Church, in the partaking of which Communion doth conſift: In this caſe they ſay the change of Names in the Prayers, as to the uſe of them, affects the Conſciences of People, as much as the change of them in the Oath of Allegiance; and therfore for the People to joyn in them, would not be <hi>to hold the unity of the Spirit,</hi> but to make themſelves Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to that which they think an unrighteous Uſurpation, which would be a great Sin.</p>
            <p>But you tell us again, <hi>That great Revolutions have happened in all Ages and Countries, and that you believe it will not eaſily be found, that ever any Chriſtians ſeparated from the Church upon the account of them.</hi> Here, my Lord, they diſtinguiſh again, and ſay, that Revolutions of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96576:10"/>are alſo of <hi>two ſorts;</hi> one in which the new Governours happen to acquire a clear and undoubted Title to the Government, and the other when they acquire the Government without a clear and undoubted Title, which happens when another claims it by a clearer Title, and proſecutes his Claim. As to the firſt ſort of Revolutions they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged with your Grace, that never any Chriſtians did, or ought to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the Church upon the account of them: But as to the ſecond they aſſert, that they commence juſt. Cauſes, as of Non-ſubjection, ſo of Separation, when owning the Right of the new Governours againſt the better Title, becomes not only a Condition to the Clergy of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing their Miniſtry, but alſo a part both in Prayers and Sacraments of the daily Offices of the Church.</p>
            <p>This, my Lord, is their Opinion; and had this ever been the Caſe of the Primitive Chriſtians, as you wrongfully ſuggeſt it was, they doubt not but their Practice would have been anſwerable thereunto: For the Primitive Chriſtians. ſay they, were Chriſtians all over, who ſerved God faithfully in the moſt difficult, as well as moſt eaſie parts of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; they were as zealous for the practical as the ſpeculative Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of Chriſtianity, and ſtood up as much for probity of Life, as purity of Faith, and Worſhip. In a word, they were as Righteous towards their Kings as towards God, and would have ſuffered as much for the Third, Fifth, Sixth, and Eighth Commandments, as for the Firſt or Second, or any Doctrine of the Creed.</p>
            <p>I have now, my Lord, repeated all the Anſwers which I have heard your Adverſaries make to your <hi>Querres,</hi> and I muſt needs beg ſo much favour from you, as to conſider me as the bare recite of them; for the ſufficiency of which, it is their part to undertake and not mine. But if they chance to prove ſufficient Anſwers, to ſay no more of them, then to eſpouſe the Party of thoſe Men, will not, as you tell your Pariſhoners, <hi>be to eſpouſe a Faction,</hi> or a Communion which is not the Communion of the Church.</p>
            <p>But you tell them <hi>how uneaſie ſoever ſome of them may be in joyning with the</hi> [altered and additiona] <hi>Prayers</hi> [then it ſeems ſome are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie at the Prayers, and what is the reaſon of that that? but] <hi>they will be ten times more uneaſie in ſeparating from you;</hi> which may be true, ſay they, with reſpect to <hi>outward eaſe,</hi> but not to the eaſe that is <hi>within</hi> And truly, my Lord, they themſelves are a ſenſible Example of what. they ſay, for you may read perfect Contentment in their looks, and perceive by converſing with them, that they enjoy their Deprivations more than ever they enjoyed the Poſſeſſions of which they are depriv'd. Oh! my Lord, had you ſeen <hi>Him of Palſgrave-Court.</hi> after his Extrution, you would have ſeen him look more Chearful, and Great, and Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable than ever; and I ſeriouſly profeſs to you, I had rather have his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Peace and Satisfaction, than his Throne with all its Revenues, and be in his Condition rather than that of any arrogant intruding Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, who can ſcoff at him now, to whom he would have formerly cringed, and from whom, before the Revolution, he would have coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a ſmile a great favour; I wiſh the time may come, when both the inſulting Scoffers may repent of it, leaſt another time ſhould come upon them like travel a Woman, when they ſhall ſay in anguiſh of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96576:10"/>Spirit— <hi>O let me die the Death of</hi> That <hi>righteous Man, and let my latter end be like his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fathermore you tell your Pariſhoners <hi>of the Heat and Turbulency, the Paſſion and Peeviſhneſs, the bitter Zeal and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs, that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Party doth naturally engage Men in.</hi> This, my Lord, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be true in all Church and State Diviſions, eſpecially with reſpect to them that are engaged on the wrong Side. It is not my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking now to determine in this Diviſion of our Church-men which Side is in the right; but this I can ſay, by experience from their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, that thoſe who have ſeparated from the Publick, have for the kind as few, and for the degree as little of thoſe troubleſome Paſſions, as any ſort of Men in the World: I appeal to your worthy Succeſſor, in St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s-Pariſh, if one of the new Biſhops was not in a very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed, and uneaſie paroxiſm of Spirit about accepting his Biſhoprick, and whether in a great heat of Paſſion he was not ready to go to her Majeſty, like Dr.<hi>B.</hi> to deſire to be excuſed. None of the deprived Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops parted with their Biſhopricks with half that reluctancy, that ſome of the accepters took them: The Epiſcopal Seals were beſpoke, and unbeſpoke, and at laſt after many Agonies and Fluctuations finally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoke again. But the deprived are calm, and ſmooth, and uniform within, their Hearts are fixt on God, and their good Principles, they are as free from bitter Zeal, as from Shame and Remorſe; and if you do not envy the Felicity of their Deprivations, I dare ſay they do not envy you their Revenues, and think you no reproach to them, if you do not think them ſo to you. But farther, my Lord, be the Paſſions never ſo great on both, or either ſide, upon the account of the Separation, Who muſt anſwer for that? Caſniſts ſay, that thoſe that are the Cauſe of any War muſt anſwer to God for all the Blood that is ſhed, and all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſtations that are committed in it; and ſo, I think, thoſe that are the Cauſe of any Separation muſt anſwer to the God of Peace and Unity for the Diviſion, and all the Heats and Paſſions and irregular Zeal, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs on both ſides that's occaſioned thereby. When there is Pope againſt Pope, Biſhop againſt Biſhop, there will be Feuds and Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities; this is now the ſad Condition of our other World, and let them look to it who have ſet up the <hi>Seconds,</hi> who in the Judgment of the <hi>African</hi> Church are none at all.</p>
            <p>But you call the deprived, <hi>warm Men,</hi> and <hi>ſome</hi> that is a <hi>few warm Men.</hi> But as for their fewneſs, my Lord, they ſay as the Orthodox, or Catholicks uſed to ſay to the World of <hi>Arians,</hi> That no Cauſe is to be tried by Numbers, that the <hi>Number</hi> is often in the wrong, and that they are but <hi>ſome</hi> that will be ſaved; for the Truth of this I refer to their former inſtances, with which you uſed to ſtop the Mouths of the Papiſts, when they boaſted of their <hi>Numbers;</hi> but I perceive from <hi>your</hi> Writers, that <hi>Numbers,</hi> and the <hi>Publick,</hi> are now become excellent Arguments for Truth. But then as for the imputation of <hi>heat,</hi> as they think it ſignifies not much, ſo they wonder you ſhould reproach them as <hi>hot Men,</hi> who apparently have ſo many <hi>Hot-heads</hi> among your ſelves. Certainly, my Lord, had you called to mind your <hi>PP—cks.</hi> and <hi>T—ns.</hi> and <hi>P—ns.</hi> and <hi>F—rs.</hi> and <hi>H—ns.</hi> and <hi>W—ms.</hi> you would have ſpoken more reſpectfully of <hi>heat,</hi> and not have been ſo ready to reproach the <hi>Jacobites</hi> as <hi>warm
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96576:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Men:</hi> For the Philoſophers, my Lord, that treat of the Paſſions, and the Uſe of them, tell us, that <hi>Heat</hi> is the active Principle, and as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in the moral as in the natural World, and a very cool Man, who ſince proved a <hi>Jacobite,</hi> once ſaying to another, <hi>Brother, Brother, God ſend you</hi> Patience: <hi>Brother,</hi> replied the warm Gentleman <hi>God ſend you more</hi> Paſſion; <hi>I am zealouſly affected in a good thing, and I wiſh you were ſo too.</hi> And I remember your good old Friend, Dr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> reflecting on ſome Men, whom you know, who condemned others as <hi>Hot-heads,</hi> for preaching againſt the <hi>Faction</hi> in the <hi>Popiſh Plot-time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſcourſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Epiſt. Dedicatory, preach'd at <hi>Aldermanbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> 1683.</note> ſaid, <hi>I am very ſenſible that in this Age we live in, ſome are ſo extraordinary Wiſe and Wary, as to cenſure and diſcourage all Men that ſpeak roundly, and act vigorouſly for the King and Church, as being more forward and buſie than is needful; but I am alſo ſenſible that if ſome Men had not ſhewn more Courage and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, than thoſe prudent Perſons, bot would have been by this time in far greater Danger than at this preſent, thanks be to God, they are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, my Lord, to apologize no longer for <hi>Heat,</hi> (which is good or bad, as the Occaſion upon, or the Cauſe in which it is uſed,) I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to your own Conſcience, Whether you do not know among the <hi>Jacobeans,</hi> as cool, and as conſidering Tempers as any you know among your Acquaintance, who yet ſeparate from the Publick upon the ſame <hi>Pretences,</hi> which you tell the People ſome <hi>warm Men ſuggeſt.</hi> I wiſh, my Lord, for the future you would take the Counſel of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> and let theſe Men alone; for if this Counſel, or this Work of theirs, be but the effect of <hi>Heat,</hi> or<note n="‡" place="margin">Page 29.</note> 
               <hi>unaccountable Humour,</hi> it will come to naught <hi>of it ſelf;</hi> but if it be of God, ye cannot overthrow it, though you may perſecute them to deſtruction, leſt haply ye be found to fight againſt God.</p>
            <p>I have now given <hi>your Grace</hi> an occaſion to review <hi>your Faremwel-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> in which, by the leave of the <hi>Gentlemen of the Veſtry,</hi> I muſt needs ſay, I think, you have reaſoned very indifferently, and-noot like your ſelf. And though thoſe Gentlemen, through the great veneration they deſervedly had for you, did not perceive the weakneſs of your Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet many others who can diſtinguiſh betwixt the Speaker, and what is ſpoken, did. Nay, I can aſſure you that ſome of the weaker Sex were ſenſible of it: <hi>Madam,</hi> ſaid a Lady to another of great Quality, <hi>You hear what my Lord ſays; Yes,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>I have heard what be ſays as well as your Ladiſhip, but he hath ſaid nothing to convince me: And if this be all he hath to ſay, I ſhall be more confirmed than I was, for I think I am able to anſwer all that I heard him ſay.</hi> To this purpoſe ſpoke that <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>moſt Vertuous Lady;</hi> and I could do no leſs then tell <hi>your Grace</hi> of it, that hereafter you may take care to print none but rational Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which it concerns you to do, not only as a Perſon of moſt vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Character, but as a great pretender to Reaſon, who in a certain time, and place, doubted if <hi>the Biſhops then ſuſpended were good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners,</hi> though you could not but grant that they were <hi>good Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>My Lord, I am your moſt faithful Monitor, and obedient. Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
